{"tossups": [{"question": "This empire was governed by the Gbara, which drew delegates from its territories across the \u201cTwelve Doors\u201d and was formed by the Kouroukan Fouga constitution. According to myth, a rooster-tipped arrow allowed this empire to win the Battle of Kirina. A ruler of this empire allegedly devalued gold throughout North Africa with his lavish gifts while on a hajj to Mecca. For the point, name this West African empire that was supplanted by the Songhai and was once ruled by Mansa Musa.", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this position held by James I and Charles I, who ruled on an island east of Ireland.", "answer": "<b> King</b> of<b> England</b> (accept equivalents such as<b> British Monarch</b>; accept<b> King</b> of<b> Scotland </b>during the first sentence; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The \u201cBloody Deeds\u201d of this politician were attacked in the Coffin Handbills. Davy Crockett stopped this man from beating Richard Lawrence with a cane after a failed assassination attempt. This man had a lifelong feud with Henry Clay due to losing an election to John Quincy Adams because of the \u201ccorrupt bargain.\u201d This mentor of Martin van Buren became the first Democratic President after winning the Election of 1828. For the point, name this 7th President of the United States.", "answer": "Andrew<b> Jackson</b> (prompt on \u201cOld Hickory\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This character is swindled out of 30,000 gold coins by the Dutch Sea Captain Mynheer Vanderdendur. This character dines at an inn with Martin and a group of men who turn out to be six deposed monarchs, including Charles Edward Stuart. This character loses his friend Jacques the Anabaptist during a massive earthquake in Lisbon. The overly-optimistic Professor Pangloss tutors, for the point, what title character of a 1759 satire by Voltaire?", "answer": "<b> Candide</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s viceroy, Diego Hurtado de Mendoza, was ousted by the Council of Thirteen in the Revolt of the Brotherhoods. Francis I was imprisoned by this ruler in the aftermath of the Battle of Pavia. Troops under this man defeated the League of Cognac to carry out the 1528 Sack of Rome. This monarch called the Diet of Worms to condemn the heresy of Martin Luther. For the point, name this father of Philip II, an extremely influential Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Charles V</b> (accept<b> Charles I of Spain</b> or<b> Carlos I of Spain</b>; prompt on \u201cCharles;\u201d do not prompt on \u201cCharles I\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this city, the murder of Mary Phagan led to severe antisemitism when Leo Frank was convicted on flimsy evidence. In 1973, Sam Massell lost a mayoral election in this city to its first black mayor, Maynard Jackson. John Bell Hood was forced to retreat from this city after a series of defeats, including one at Peachtree Creek. This city\u2019s Centennial Park was bombed during the 1996 Summer Olympics. William Sherman started his March to the Sea in, for the point, what largest city in Georgia?", "answer": "<b> Atlanta</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1970, a group of Yippies \u201cinvaded\u201d this location in protest of the Vietnam War, seizing control of Tom Sawyer Island. Nikita Khrushchev asked if gangsters had taken control of this location after he was barred from visiting due to security concerns. At this location\u2019s opening day, parents threw their children over crowds of people to get them onto rides like the King Arthur Carousel. For the point, name this Anaheim amusement park, the first built by Walt Disney.", "answer": "<b> Disneyland</b> (do not accept or prompt on Disneyworld)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was the site of the Baltimore Crisis, in which two American sailors were stabbed after one of them spit on a photo of Arturo Prat. In this country, the democratically-elected Salvador Allende [ah-YEHN-day] was overthrown by the American-backed Augusto Pinochet. This country secured its territory in the Atacama desert by defeating a Bolivian-Peruvian alliance in the War of the Pacific. For the point, name this South American country governed from Santiago.", "answer": "<b> Chile</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this event, Pedro de Arbu\u00b4es was assassinated in La Seo Cathedral. Over 7,000 women were killed during this event as part of a witch trial targeting Logro\u02dcno. Auto-de-f\u00b4e was a common punishment in this period, which was spearheaded by Tom\u00b4as de Torquemada. The Alhambra Decree was passed during this period to expel Jews from the Iberian Peninsula. For the point, name this period in which non-Catholics were forced to convert in Spain.", "answer": "Spanish<b> Inquisition</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Under the rule of King Agum III, forces from this city burned Dur-Enlil in a war against the Sealand Dynasty. Tukulti-Ninurta seized control of this city after defeating Kassite king Kashtilash IV. The King of Judah, Jehoikhan, was deposed by forces from this city under Nebuchadnezzar II. A law code governing this city called for an \u201ceye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth.\u201d For the point, name this Mesopotamian city led by Hammurabi, the site of a possibly legendary Hanging Gardens.", "answer": "<b> Babylon</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A piece inspired by this country includes a mandolin solo in its \u201cOctober Harvest Festival\u201d movement and later depicts a battle in its \u201cCircuses\u201d movement. A \u201cPilgrim\u2019s March\u201d appears in an A major piece named for this country, Mendelssohn\u2019s Fourth Symphony. A piece set in this country features a recording of a nightingale and depicts the title \u201cPines\u201d on the Appian Way. For the point, name this country that inspired Ottorino Resphigi\u2019s work<em> Festivals of Rome</em>.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b> (accept<b> Italian</b> Republic; accept<b> Italia</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In the prelude to this conflict, one side threatened to arrest British reporters aboard the<em> Haimun</em>. Anatoly Stessel was forced to surrender Port Arthur during this conflict after the disastrous Battle of Liaoyang. Theodore Roosevelt helped negotiate an end to this conflict in the Treaty of Portsmouth, which was signed after the Baltic Fleet was defeated at the Battle of Tsushima. The southern Sakhalin Island was seized during, for the point, what 1905 conflict between a European power led by Nicholas II and an upstart Asian empire?", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War (accept<b> Nichiro</b> senso)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This person was given the task of determining whether or not a blacksmith lied when claiming that a crown for the King of Syracuse was made with pure gold. Water and grain can be lifted using a screw named for this person. This scientist discovered that the weight of the fluid displaced by an object is equal to the exerted force on the object. For the point, name this Ancient Greek who, when he discovered the principle of buoyancy, exclaimed \u201cEureka!\u201d", "answer": "<b> Archimedes</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "In a massive TV disappointment, Geraldo Rivera hosted a 2-hour long special about a vault owned by this man at the Lexington Hotel, only to find it was filled with dirt. This man, debilitated by syphilis, was stabbed by James Lucas while imprisoned at Alcatraz. The St. Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre was likely carried out on the orders of, for the point, what Chicago gangster who was arrested for tax evasion?", "answer": "Alphonse \u201cAl\u201d<b> Capone</b> (prompt on \u201cScarface\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The reign of this ruler included an ill-fated attempt by Earl Chatham to capture the Netherlands in the Walcheren Expedition. The only British prime minister to be assassinated, Spencer Perceval, served this ruler, who was also aided by the Ministry of All the Talents under Lord Grenville. William Pitt helped pave the way for a regency to rule in the name of this ruler, who suffered from porphyria in his later years. For the point, name this English king who lost the thirteen colonies during the American Revolution.", "answer": "<b> George III</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During the Mexican-American War, John Sloat occupied this modern-day state after seizing control of Monterey Bay. William B. Ide led a revolt in this state secretly supported by John C. Fremont that introduced the Bear Flag. Workers in this state discovered a precious metal at Sutter\u2019s Mill, setting off a mass migration. For the point, name this state where the Gold Rush of 1849 led to the growth of towns like San Francisco.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A portion of this island was occupied in Operation Banner, a response to the August 1969 riots. The Good Friday Agreement ended a conflict on this island which included groups like the Ulster Defense Association. In 1972, 26 civilians on this island were killed by soldiers in Derry during Bloody Sunday. The Troubles took place on, for the point, what British isle where the IRA carried out attacks in cities like Belfast?", "answer": "<b> Ireland</b> (accept<b> Eire</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}